<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon teaching discretion in matters of religion, and touching certayne abuses nowe in the Churche preached at Paules Crosse the 21. of Nouember by Robert Temple Bachelor in Diuinitie sometimes of Magdalene Colledge in Oxforde.</title>
            <author>Temple, Robert, Bachelor in Diuinitie.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836820</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836820</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1190:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon teaching discretion in matters of religion, and touching certayne abuses nowe in the Churche preached at Paules Crosse the 21. of Nouember by Robert Temple Bachelor in Diuinitie sometimes of Magdalene Colledge in Oxforde.</title>
                  <author>Temple, Robert, Bachelor in Diuinitie.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By R. B[ourne] for Edward Aggas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1592.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Sermon teaching <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in matters of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and touching certayne <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes nowe in the Churche:</hi> Preached at Paules Croſſe <hi>the</hi> 21. <hi>of Nouember by</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Temple Bachelor in <hi>Diuinitie ſometimes of Magdalene</hi> Colledge in Oxforde.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern. Cant: ſerm.</hi> 49.</bibl>
               <p>Quo zelus feruidior, ac vehementior ſpiritus profuſior<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> charitas, eo vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantiori opus eſt ſcientia quae zelum ſupprimat, ſpiritum temperet, ordinet charitatem.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by R. B. for Edward Aggas. 1592.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the right Reuerende</hi> father in god <hi>Iohn</hi> by Gods permiſsion, Biſhop of London, <hi>my ſpeciall good Lord, all</hi> humble dutye acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to youre Lo. pleaſure (right reuerende Father) I haue copied out this Sermon, and let it go to the preſſe, remouing (at length though with much a do) a common reaſon that diſwades verie many, and did for a time diſcourage my ſelfe: I meane the peruerſe cauillatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuch, as call into queſtion other mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a greate deale buſier to finde a fault, then do any good, as in deede it is eaſier to reprehende then iudge arighte, and miſlike then do the like. I am ſo farre (I proteſt) from ſelfe loue or lyking, that I am ſtill affrayde leaſt ſome thinge of other bee committed
<pb facs="tcp:1109:3"/> whiche being ſette out abroade, can not bee called in againe Manie may flatter themſelues in a fonde conceite of there owne doings, and delight in the fauorable iudgemente of their friendes, but they ſhall finde it farre otherwiſe, when there workes come once to a vulgar protractation. I moſt humblie beſeech your Lo. to defend with your accuſtomed fauour my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthye labour, and earneſtlye praye my Bretheren in the Miniſtrie, to laie aſide all former conceaued opinion againſte the matter, and hartely deſire euerie good reader beſides to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue euerie thing with a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as I for his ſake in euery point haue ſpoken my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience. At your L. Mannor houſe at Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham: Aprill 22. 1592.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your L. in all humble dutie</hi> Robert Temple.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text 1 Cor. 14. verſ. 1.</bibl>
                  <p>Follow after loue and couet ſpirituall giftes, &amp; rather that ye may propheſie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle hauing hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before at large the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde giftes of the ſpirite, and treating theruppon of loue, the excellent waye of all giftes, purpoſing to handle propheſie the worthyeſt gifte of all, hee ſeemeth to make his entraunce by concluſion of all hee ſpake of before: and bids the Corinthians a Gods name to couet ſpirituall gifts but with all to followe loue, and rather that they maye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie.<note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſion.</note> Before I come to ſpeake of two principall points herein conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, firſt loue the moderation of all giftes, ſecondly propheſie the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent gifte of all: Wee are generally to obſerue the onely matter and worke of all giftes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:4"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 68.18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſ 4.8.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt aſcending vp on high led captiuity captiue, &amp; gaue gifts vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; the ſame vnto euery one of vs by grace according to the meaſure of the gift of chriſt, and to this end the repayring of the Sainctes, the worke of the miniſtery &amp; the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat gifts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> By gifts are ment operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; faculties beſtowed diuerſly, &amp; peculiarlye to profit the church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.<note place="margin">VVhy called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irituall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fies. Author of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fies.</note> They be called ſpirituall gifts: Firſt for authoritie, ſecondlie for office.</p>
            <p>The Authour of all gifts is the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God. <hi>For there are diuerſities of giftes, but the ſame ſpirit, and there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of adminiſtrations, but the ſame Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 12.4.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; there are diuerſities of operations, but God is the ſame that worketh all in all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">4.5.6.8.</note> So that all kinde of gifts and callings <hi>(as propheſies, teaching, exhortation, the word of wiſdome, the worde of knowledge, fayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>healing, great workes, diſcerning of ſpirits, diuerſities of tongues, Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Euangeliſts, Paſtors, Teachers) one and the ſelfe ſame ſpirite worketh, diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to euery man ſeuerally as he will.</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe
<pb facs="tcp:1109:4"/> ſaythe: Vnum flumen,<note place="margin">Ambroſ. ſpi ſanct. Gratian. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> ſed multi donorum ſpiritualium me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus, hoc flumen exit de fonte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae: <hi>Many riuers but one flood from which they doe all iſſue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>this commeth out of the fountaine of life.</hi> For whiche cauſe the holy ſpiryt (albeit properly the thirde perſon in trinitye, and Effector of all giftes) is taken for the gift of God,<note place="margin">Act. 19.20.</note> as appeareth in the queſtion of St. <hi>Paule</hi> to certaine diſciples at Epheſus, <hi>haue ye receaued the holy ghoſt ſince yee beleued?</hi> Meaning whither the graces of the ſpirit were giuen to Chriſtes diſciples. Auſten ſaith ſomewhat confuſedly,<note place="margin">Aug. Lau. Enchirid. Cap. <hi>37.</hi>
               </note> as it may ſeeme, yet truely Et vtique ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſanctus dei donum eſt, quod qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem et ipſum eſt equale donanti. <hi>And verelie the holy ghoſt is the gift of God, the which in very deede is equall to the giuer</hi> diſcerning the ſpirits by a double no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the authour of all gifts ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and ſo it is not the gift of God, but God himſelfe eſſentially equall to the father and the ſonne and againe for
<pb facs="tcp:1109:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> the verye giftes themſelues, as either they were beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtles in the daye of Pentecoſt, or as the faythfull haue the holye Spirite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Colloſ. 3.1. Act. 3.24.</note>
               <hi>Chriſt then is come and gone, hee ſittes at his Fathers right hand, the Heauens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teynes him vntill the reſtitution of all thinges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> 
               <hi>he is our Aduocate with the father and liueth for euer, making interceſſion for vs, without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie great is the miſterie of Godlyneſſe which is:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>God is manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentils, beleued on in the world, and receaued vp in glory.</hi> But now the maiſter, and Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the faculties in his abſence is his ſpirite: For as he deſerued grace for vs by his death, triumphed ouer death by his reſurrection, ſits at his fathers right hand by his aſcention: So hee hath left the ſpirit obtayning and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing all requiſite, and neceſſarie graces for his Church. The ſpirite is Chriſtes vicegerent and Preſident of
<pb facs="tcp:1109:5"/> his church, the church being like vnto a Schoole wherein the holye ghoſt teacheth the faythfull all godlyneſſe.<note place="margin">Rom. 10.4.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt is the ende of the lawe, for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſake vnto euery one that beleueth, and nowe throughe the ſpirite wee wayte for the hope of righteouſnes through fayth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5.5.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.17</note> 
               <hi>He is the fulfiller of the Lawe and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, for hee came not to deſtroy them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſtom. adorand. ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Galat. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Eſay. 54.13 Ioh. 6.45. Ioh. 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>but to fullfill them. And ſo is the ſpirite the fullfilling of the goſpel. The lawe was our ſcholemayſter to bringe vs to Chriſt, that wee mighte bee made righteous throughe fayth, now wee are all taught of God, as the holye ghoſt ſent by the father in Chriſtes name teacheth vs all things, and bringes all things into our remembraunce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>as hee hathe told vs. As manie as receiued him, to them he gaue a prerogatiue to be the ſonnes of god,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>and now hath god ſent foorth the ſpirite of his ſonne, whiche cryeth</hi> Abba <hi>father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.16</note> 
               <hi>and the ſame ſpirite witneſſeth with our ſpirite, that wee are the Children of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe they bee called gifts ſpirituall</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:6"/> for the office,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffice of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iftes.</note> either in reſpect of the matter, <hi>for it is the wiſedome of God in a miſterie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 2.6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phe. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>euen the hid wiſedome which God determined before the worlde vnto our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, a grace giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preach the vnſearchable riches of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>a goſpel ſent downe by the holye Ghoſte from Heauen, the which the Angels deſire to beholde,</hi> or of the ſucceſſe and fruite,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 4.20. Theſ. 1.5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Theſ. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>for the kingdome of God is not in word, but in power, neither is the goſpell in word onely, but in power of the holye ghoſt, to bee receaued not as the word of men, but as it is in deede the worde of God which worketh in them that beleue.</hi> Paule <hi>may plant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 3.7.</note> Apollos <hi>water, but God muſte giue the increaſe, whoſoeuer is anye thing he muſt ſaye with</hi> St. Paule, <hi>by the grace of God I am that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.10.</note> &amp; therefore a woorke impoſſible for man to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme without worthy graces of the holye ghoſt. If wee doe conſider the mutuall edification of the Church, the matter is indifferent without anie reſpect at all,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note> 
               <note place="margin">28</note> 
               <hi>for wee are all the ſonnes of God by fayth in Chriſt Ieſus, all one in him,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:6"/> Abrahams ſeede, and heires by promiſe, a choſen generation, a royall prieſthood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>an holy nation, a people ſet at libertie to ſhewe foorth the vertue of him that hath called vs out of darkenes into a wonderfull light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>in him that loued vs and waſhed vs from our ſinnes in his blood, we are made Kinges and Prieſtes vnto God euen the Father.</hi> But if wee doe marke the ordinarye gouernment of the Churche there is verie great ods.<note place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>For the holie ghoſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth out ſome from amongeſt the reſt to the Biſhopricke of the flocke, and ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Church:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17 1. Theſ. 5.13</note> 
               <hi>To be obeyed as ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers becauſe they watche and muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt for ſoules, to be had in looue for the woorkes ſake labouring among the people, and being ouer them in the Lord.</hi> And as there are giftes of the ſpirite common to the faithfull <hi>loue, ioy, peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, gentlenes, goodnes, fayth, meekenes, temperancy, againſt which there is no law:</hi> So theſe giftes whereof the Apoſtle ſpeaketh we haue named them a litle before in the beginning. <hi>Propheſie,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:7"/> Teaching,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>Exhortation, and the like,</hi> are giftes of a ſeuerall and peculiar functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.8.28.</note> But as with this community of giftes vnto all the faythfull, there is a diſcretion and order in the Churche for ornament: So giftes are alwaies ioyned with theſe offices, for edifica-of the Church, and both for increaſe of faith, and knoweledge by vnitie in Chriſt. The ſpirite of grace, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies from the beginning diſcerneth the elect from the numeroſitie of the reſt refuſed, and diſanulled, euermore furniſheth ſuch as be called to this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of office in the Church with dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and ſufficiencie of giftes. When Chriſte called foorth his Apoſtles to preach, hee ſent them with giftes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>the kingdome of GOD is at hande heale the Sicke, cleanſe the Leapers, rayſe vp the deade you haue freelie receaued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.6.8.20.</note> 
               <hi>giue freely, it is not you that ſpeake, but the ſpirit of your father which ſpeaketh in you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>and in the daye of</hi> Pentecoſt, <hi>they were all filled with the holy ghoſt, &amp; began to ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:1109:7"/> with other tongues as the ſpirite gaue them vtteraunce. And the ſeuen men whom the Apoſtles did chuſe to the office of the Deaconſhip, were full of the holie ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 6.3.5.8</note> 
               <hi>and of wiſedome and faythe, and ſo knowne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they layde their handes on them, and</hi> Steuen <hi>full of faythe and power aboue the reſt, and of manye miracles among the people, ſo that a number of them of the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues diſputing with him, were not able to reſiſt the wiſedome and the ſpirite where with he ſpake.</hi> Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tertul: exbo. ad castit.</note> aleadging the reaſon of the Apoſtles words,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.40.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; I thinke alſo I haue the ſpirite of God,</hi> idcir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cò hoc dixit vt ſibi Apoſtoli faſtigium redderet. <hi>Therefore hee ſayde ſo to ſhewe the authoritie of an Apoſtle.</hi> Spiritum quidem Dei etiam fideles habent, ſed non omnes fideles ſunt Apoſtoli, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè enim Apoſtoli ſpiritum ſanctum habent qui plenè habent in operibus Prophetiae efficatiam virtutis at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentorum linguam, non quaſi ex parte quod ceteri. <hi>Truelie the faythfull haue alſo the ſpirite of God, but all that bee
<pb facs="tcp:1109:8"/> faythfull bee not Apoſtles, for the Apoſtles haue the holy ghoſt properlie, inſomuch as they haue in their Propheſie an effectuall working of power, and vtteraunce of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and that aboundantlye, not as it were in part like other:</hi> Not then the vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſeuerall office, but meaſure of gifts neceſſarie to their offices, not the worthyneſſe of ſuch as be called.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt part Loue the rule of all giftes.</note>Nowe the Corinthians reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed very gratiouſlie with all theſe giftes, yet conuerting them (not as they ought to the glorie of God, and edifying one of an other, but to oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and contention among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:) St. Paule aloweth their ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of giftes, but withall ſettes downe a moderation by looue, for loue diſpoſeth euerie woorke vnto a perfection. The principall ende of all actions is the glorye of God, <hi>for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wee doe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>wee muſt do all to the glorie of God,</hi> but the way to bring vs to this ende is loue, all thinges diuine, and ayme at loue, <hi>for the ende of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement
<pb facs="tcp:1109:8"/> is looue oute of a pure hart, and a good conſcience and of fayth vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.5.</note> This the Apoſtle prooues verye largely, <hi>naming it a more excellent way of the beſt gifts, that although a man do ſpeak with the tongues of men, and Angells, and haue not loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.31 1. Cor. 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>hee is like a ſounding braſſe and a tinckling Cymball: And although hee had the gift of Propheſie, and knewe all ſecrets, and all knowledge, yea if hee had all fayth, ſo that hee coulde remooue moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and had no loue, hee were nothing: And though hee fedde the poore withall</hi> his goodes, and though hee gaue his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to be burned, &amp; haue no <hi>loue it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth nothing.</hi> So againe to the ſame purpoſe, hee willes the Epheſians to <hi>followe the truth in loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.13.16</note> 
               <hi>and in all thinges to growe vp vnto him, which is the head, which is Chriſt, by whom all the bodye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing coupled &amp; knit togither by euery ioynt for the furniture thereof according to the effectuall power, which is in the meaſure of euerye, parte receaueth the increaſe of the bodie vnto the edefieng of it ſelfe in looue.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:9"/> A man may bee endued with manie other giftes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 8.3.</note> and yet bee vngodlie, but if anye man looue God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 12.7.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame is knowne</hi> of God. The ende of all giftes is vnitye, for the <hi>manifeſtation of the ſpirite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>is giuen to euerie one to profit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. Nowe loue endeuoureth to keepe the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the ſpirite in the bond of peace, and giues no offence, neither to the Iewes, nor to the Grecians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 10.31.</note> 
               <hi>nor to the Church of god, but followeth thoſe thinges whiche concerne peace, and wherewith one may edefie one an other.</hi> Whatſoeuer either precept or counſell is ſpecially ſet down in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath relation to loue, as wee loue God for himſelfe, and one an other for Gods ſake. Chriſtianitie is where the ſpirite is, and where the ſpirite is, there is loue.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>For God is loue, and he that dwelleth in loue, dwelleth in god, &amp; god in him:</hi> The loue wherewith god loueth vs ſhed abroad in our harts by the holy ghoſt which is giuen vnto vs,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note> is onlye theirs which fulfill the royall law,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe, loue
<pb facs="tcp:1109:9"/> diſcerneth the merite of the worke</hi> in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, from the ſemblaunce in vnitie,<note place="margin">Aug. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſt. tract. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> as Gods tradition of his ſonne from Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das prodition. The one was of loue, the other of couetouſnes.<note place="margin">Luk. 7.38 4</note> 
               <hi>Maries en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaynment from Symons hoſpitallitye, many ſinnes were forgiuen hir,</hi> for ſhee loued much,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſome mens preaching <hi>of conſcience, &amp; ſomes vnder a pretence, the one of goodwill, the other thoroughe enuie and ſtrife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aguſt. ciuit. dei lib. <hi>9.</hi> ca <hi>21.</hi> Aguſt. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſt. tract. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>godly knowledg from the</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, as greate as their knowledge is they haue no loue. Almes deedes in compaſſion, from liberalitye in vaine glory. Loue doth doth ſeeke the praiſe of God in almes, but vaine glorye the praiſe of man.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.18 <hi>Aguſt. Iho.</hi> 3. <hi>tract.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Godly feare from ſlauiſh feare, for feare hath paynefulnes, but perfect loue caſteth out feare,</hi> loue indeed is the inviſible vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſpiririt. All ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoeuer, are but the forme, loue is the roote, faith is like vnto the ſence,<note place="margin">Aug. hom. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> but loue vnto the health of the bodie. <hi>Austen</hi> ſaith that a man maye haue Baptiſme and yet bee wicked,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:10"/> 
               <hi>Prophecie (eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that notable gift</hi> that <hi>Paule</hi> here prefers) and yet be wicked, take the ſacrament of the bodie and blood of the Lord, and yet be wicked, be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a Chriſtian, and yet bee wicked, habere ſacramenta iſta omnia, et ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus eſſe poteſt. Habere autem cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem, et malus eſſe non poteſt, hoc eſt ergo proprium donum. <hi>Hee maye haue all theſe ſacraments, and yet be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but hee cannot bee wicked if hee haue loue, this is therefore a proper gift.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this were well learned of a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in theſe dayes, who take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be notable fellowes, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cenſors of all other, it would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, and keepe in manie miſchiefes which daylie breake out to the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous hurt of the Church, as Pride, Enuie, Indiſcretion, Innouatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pride through knowledge, Enuie throughe aemulation, Indiſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through zeale, Innouation through ſchiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pride tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge.</note>For commonlie Pride is where knowledge is, this ſame, Sermo ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:10"/> 
               <hi>word of knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.8 Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> very hardlie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſapere ad ſobrietate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſobrietie, for knowledge puffeth vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.1.</note> and maketh a man verie ſingularlie proud, as if hee were the onely man, and none like him in the world. A pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous matter (I tell you) is inflamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through knowledge,<note place="margin">Iren. lib. cap. <hi>1.31.</hi>
               </note> that marde <hi>Tacianus</hi> after his maiſter <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome, &amp; made him a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heriticke,<note place="margin">Bern. cant. ſerm. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bern.</hi> notes it to be the onely prancke of all ſuch: Captare gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſingularitate ſcientiae, <hi>to gette glorie by ſingularitie of learning.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. reſur. domin. ſer. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And I praie you (as <hi>Ber.</hi> ſaith againe) quaemaior ſuperbia, quam vt vnus homo totae congregationi iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ſum prae ferat, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſe ſolus habeat ſpiritum dei. <hi>Can there bee anye greater Pride then for one man to ſette his owne iudgment before the whole Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as though hee and none elſe hath the ſpirit of God.</hi> Now where loue is there can be no preſumption, and mayſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of doctrine, <hi>Loue doth aedefie, and doth not boaſt it ſelfe, neyther is puffed vp,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:11"/> Auſten ſayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. ſerm. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note> Amate ſcientiam, ſed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teponite charitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſcientia ſi ſola ſit, inflat, charitas vero edificat, et non per mittit ſcientiam inflari. <hi>Loue knowledge, but preferre loue, knoweledge if it bee alone puffeth vp, but loue edefieth, and doth not ſuffer knoweledge to be puffed vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Enuye tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Aug. ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioh. ſerm. <hi>53.</hi>
               </note>With pride commonlye enuie is ioyned, for pride is nothing elſe then a loue of excellencie, which breedes a peruerſe imitation againſte the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles rule.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.31</note> 
               <hi>Deſire you the beſt gifts, and yet I will ſhewe you a more excellent waie,</hi> (meaning loue) and againe <hi>foraſmuch as ye couet ſpirituall giftes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.12</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke that ye may excell to the edefieng of the Church.</hi> And ſo brings forth that carnall emulation ſpoken of by the Apoſtle amongſt the workes of the fleſh.<note place="margin">Galat. 5.20.</note> Nowe loue is in this a remedie,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.4.</note> 
               <hi>for loue enuieth not. If there bee any comfort in loue, if any fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the ſpirite, nothing is done through contention,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Philip. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>or vaine glory, but in meekenes of minde, euerie one eſteemes an other bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then himſelfe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. hom. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> ſayth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaude
<pb facs="tcp:1109:11"/> illi, cui deus aliquam gratiam dedit, et potes in illo, quod in te non potes. <hi>Bee glade in his behalfe to whom God hath giuen any grace, and thou mayſt doe that in him, which thou canſt not doe in thy ſelfe. Peraduenture (ſayth</hi> Auſten) <hi>hee hath virginity, loue him,</hi> &amp; <hi>it is thine. Againe thou haſt more patience then he, let him loue thee, and tis his. Hee can watch a night at his ſtudie, if thou doſt not enuie him, his ſtudie is thine. Perchaunce thou canſt faſt a great deale more, if he loue thee, thy faſting is his,</hi> hoc ideo, quia in illo tu es, per proprietatem non es tu, per charitatem tu es. <hi>This is the reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou art in him, by propertie thou art not, by charitie thou art.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. altitud. cord. ſerm. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that on a time one tolde him that hee ſawe a laye Moncke in whom he did recken 30. vertues, <hi>whereof</hi> ſayth he, <hi>I finde not one in my ſelfe, and perhaps</hi> ſayth Bernard, <hi>he had not ſo great a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue amongſt the reſt as this was,</hi> religioſae emulationis humilitas: <hi>Humble emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in matters of religion.</hi> And in
<pb facs="tcp:1109:12"/> deede there is no gift greater.<note place="margin">Math. 3.15.</note> When <hi>Iohn</hi> earneſtly put Chriſt backe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>I haue neede to be baptiſed of thee, and comeſt thou vnto mee? Hee made him this anſwere. Let bee nowe, for thus it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vs to fulfill all righteouſenes,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs that perfect righteouſnes hath alwayes godlie humbleneſſe.<note place="margin">1. Co. 13.2.3.</note> When the Apoſtle ſheweth the corruption of manie gifts, if charitie be away, hee ſaith, <hi>all ſecreats, all knowledge, all fayth, all goodes,</hi> to ſignifie that all is nothing where is enuie and emulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, two ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie contraries vnto loue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Teale with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>An other miſchife we ſpake of, is zeale without diſcretion, for where the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit enableth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with notable giftes, <hi>zeale</hi> for the moſt part <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth &amp; eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him vp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.9.</note> that verie ſeldome is that rule of the Apoſtle performed <hi>ſpiritu feruentes, feruent in ſpirite.</hi> But rather that wherewith the Apoſtle findeth fault,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.21</note> 
               <hi>zelum dei habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſed non ex ſcientia,</hi> they haue the zeale of god, but not accordinge to knowledge. If zeale
<pb facs="tcp:1109:12"/> bee not gouerned, it inclineth verye quickelie to vices.<note place="margin">Berna. epiſt. <hi>89</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Barnard</hi> writing to a freind of his (&amp; allowing his zeale) willeth him to haue a zeale, but accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to knowledge, vt cautus ſis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iora minoribus non impedire, <hi>that</hi> ſaith he <hi>thou do beware thou hinder not greater matters for leſſe.</hi> For in matters of vehement, and hote emulation, we marre all if wee order not loue with diſcretion, and zeale with loue.<note place="margin">Berna. cant. ſerm. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inflammet charitas, informet ſcientia, firmet conſtantia. <hi>Let loue kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle thy zeale, knowledg inſtruct it, ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſettle it,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi> Wee maye verye well compare zeale to a fierce horſe, if he haue not a bridle: a voice that is harſh, if a man contend, and ſtraine it to hie: an vnhappie childe if hee haue not a rodde: and a flame of fire if it bee not quenched: for ſo is zeale withoute loue, and euen ſo is the zeale of manie for lacke of loue, fierce, contentions childiſhe, the verye firebrand of the Church.
<pb facs="tcp:1109:13"/> It is a godly thing to bee zealous, yet a right zeale is <hi>according to knowledg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 10.2.</note> &amp; it is better howſoeuer, to haue <hi>a zeale (althoughe without knoweledge) then to haue no zeale at all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ig. re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and yet better to haue neither zeale, nor knowledge, then haue no loue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>novation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiſme.</note>The laſte of all is innouation, the verie handmaide of the other, whiche bringeth in the corruption and abuſe of Gods good giftes by Schiſme, a fault in the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> telleth them) <hi>that in all thinges being made rich in Chriſt in all kind of ſpeaches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor 15.7.10.12.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; all knowledge, ſo that they were not deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any kind of gift,</hi> yet they had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention among them, <hi>euery one of them ſaying, I am</hi> Paules, <hi>I am</hi> Apollos, <hi>I am</hi> Cephas, <hi>and I am</hi> Chriſtes, as though <hi>Chriſt</hi> was deuided or <hi>Paule</hi> crucified, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Such a fault is nowe a dayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, where manie vnlearned in this, that <hi>things indifferent are tollerable,</hi> &amp; that <hi>pollution commeth not by commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of ſacraments, but by conſent of ſinne</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:13"/> doe thereupon ſequeſter themſelues from the publique Congregation of Chriſtians, to a priuate ſegregation of Schiſmatickes, and ſo by diſcention <hi>bring into the Church, as it were, an infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall diſſipation of the bodie, and a verye helliſhe perturbation of the members of Chriſt, as though</hi> Iudah,<note place="margin">Greg. nazia orat. <hi>1.</hi> pac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Iſraell <hi>did not belong to one principallytie, nor</hi> Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>and</hi> Samaria, <hi>to one heauenly</hi> Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>And</hi> Paule, <hi>and</hi> Appollos, <hi>and</hi> Cephas <hi>for whom and againſt whom all this ſame ſwelling is, and Chriſt himſelfe and all Chriſtians are not all one.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 26.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> ſayth, conferring the place of <hi>Dauid, I waſh my hands in innocencie oh Lord,</hi> and againe <hi>Lorde I haue loued the habitation of thy houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> 
               <hi>and the place where thine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth,</hi> with the ſaying of ſainct <hi>Paule.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.20</note> 
               <hi>In a good houſe are not onely veſſels of golde and ſiluer, but alſo of wood and of earth, and ſome for honour, and ſome for diſhonour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. parm. Epiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Ideo quippe tollerabat no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centes, non deſereret innocentes, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quibus lauabat manus, quia dilige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat
<pb facs="tcp:1109:14"/> ſpeciem domus Domini, quae ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies in vaſis honoralibus fuit, nec propter vaſa que erant in contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſe a magna domo ſeperabat, ſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os in vnitate vnius domus tolerabat a quibus ſe non imitando ſeruabat. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid did therefore</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>let the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked alone, leaſt he ſhould goe from the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, with whom hee did waſhe his handes, for hee loued the beawtye of Gods houſe which beawtie was in veſſels of honour, neyther went hee aſunder from the greate habitation becauſe of the veſſels of reproch, but kept himſelfe well enough from them, not doing as they did whom hee ſuffred in one and the ſelfe ſame houſe.</hi> Theſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes ſhoulde learne of Auſten to loue the bewtye of Gods Church, whiche is the honourable ſocietie of the godlie howeſoeuer mixed with the ſhamefull corruption of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and not forſake the ornament of the one, for the diſhonour of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſeeking a fellowſhipe of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in euery poynte whiche can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:1109:14"/> be founde.<note place="margin">Num. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Moyſes</hi> did wiſh that <hi>all the Lordes people coulde Propheſie, &amp; that the Lord would put his ſpirite vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. St.</hi> Paule did wiſh that all men were like himſelfe in (puritie) and <hi>that all did ſpeake ſtraunge langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but rather that they propheſied.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 1. Cor. 14</note> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. ſecu. Ioh. ſerm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> wiſheth that all woulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member loue, and brings this reaſon. Sola eſt enim quae et vincit omnia, et ſine qua nihil valent omnia, et v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> fuerit trahit ad ſe omnia. <hi>For only loue both ouercommeth all things, and without loue all things are nothing worth, &amp; whereſoeuer loue is, it draweth al things vnto it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an. parte o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> If anie of vs (Chriſtians) be aſked the queſtion (ſayth <hi>Gregory Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi>) what we worſhip, Promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt reſpondere, quod charitatem, veneremur: <hi>The anſwere is ready, wee worſhip charitye.</hi> Wee had need crye out and writ no longer againſt falſe Catholiques (ſola fides) <hi>Fayth onlie,</hi> but againſte falſe Proteſtantes (ſola Charitas) <hi>loue only,</hi> faction aboundeth,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:15"/> loue abateth, let fayth onelye iuſtifie, but loue onely rectifie.</p>
            <p>But let vs come nere the ſore, and touch the verie wound of the church, &amp; I praie you with patience, becauſe I will vtter nothing but that euerye ones conſcience ſhall by experience acknowledge true <hi>Gregorie Naziazen</hi> lamenting the deſperate ſtate of the church in his time through the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable furie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. Nect. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſcop. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctant.</note> and miſerable afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſame, reckneth vp many he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes. Firſt thoſe of <hi>Arrius</hi> or <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxius,</hi> an inſolent ſect, aſſembling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in priuate Churches, as it were by lawefull permiſſion: Againe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians</hi> whoſe factious contention grewe to that temeritie and madneſſe, that they tooke vnto themſelues the titles &amp; places of Biſhopes, boaſting of <hi>Eleuſius</hi> the author of their election. But (ſayth hee) there is one <hi>Eunomius</hi> and his ſect the inwarde plague and miſcheife of the Church, who think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it a great deale out of his waie if
<pb facs="tcp:1109:15"/> hee drawe not all with himſelfe into deſtruction and daunger, &amp; yet theſe things are tollerable: But of all church trobles, the <hi>Apolinariſts</hi> libertie is moſt licentious, I am to certefie youre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence (he meaneth <hi>Nectarius</hi>) that a litle booke is come to my handes of <hi>Apollinaris,</hi> wherein ſuch thinges are written as exceedes all peruerſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes that euer were.<note place="margin">Conueticles of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</note> I will haue you conſider, that if theſe haue common liberty of priuat metings, it is nothing elſe but to eſteeme their doctrine tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then ours, and you know that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye thing nature ſuffereth not two contrary doctrines of one &amp; the ſame point to be true. Any that will, may verye well conſider the ſame to be the preſent calamitie and ieopardy of our Church, and as <hi>Gregorie</hi> to <hi>Nectarius,</hi> ſo I appeale to our magiſtrates for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe. Firſt and for moſt wee haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs <hi>Paules Ieſuites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chem. Exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> prefat. par. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> a murren ſect of hereticks that infect the purenes of the Goſpell, &amp; a cruell ſort of bloody
<pb facs="tcp:1109:16"/> ones that abiure a lawefull allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce to their Prince,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s. Hum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. Cur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ax.</note> &amp; naturall loue to their Countrie, and by forreine conſpiracie abroade put in practiſe at home the death of the one and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the other:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſuites.</note> Theſe thinke they doe God good ſeruice to ſlaye his anoynted,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſebius. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cap. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> &amp; murther his ſaincts, endeuoring <hi>as did the Impoſters in</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria <hi>in the dayes of</hi> Decius <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame the peoples deſire with a cuſtomed ſuperſtition of the Countrye, and make them beleeue that the worſhipping of Idols, and murdering of Proteſtants is pietie: Auguſt.</hi> exclaimes againſt ſuch a zeale,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>guſt. Iho. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. tract. <hi>93.</hi>
               </note> ó error horrendus, ò execrabilis ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas, Zelum Dei habent ſed non ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ſcientiam, obſequium ſe pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant praeſtare deo interficiendo famu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los Dei. <hi>Oh horrible error, oh exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable blindeneſſe, they haue a zeale, but not accordinge to knoweledge, they thinke they doe GOD good ſeruice in killinge the Seruauntes of GOD.</hi> But I will not make manye wordes aboute
<pb facs="tcp:1109:16"/> them, onelye this I ſaye, as they be our countrie men by Nation, pity their liues, as they bee Papiſtes in weakeneſſe, labour to conuert them, but as they be heretiques in pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie, and Traytors to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, let the Lawe puniſhe them, and I praye God either turne their harts from whetting anie more ſwordes to ſhed the blood of the Lordes anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or returne the ſharpeſt ſwordes from the pointe with a cutting edge on bothe ſides in vp to the verye hiltes in their owne heartes blood. Oh Lorde lette ELIZABETH floriſhe with a Crowne of glorye vppon her heade, and a Scepter of Tryumphe in her hande, and ſtill <hi>waſhe her feete in the bloode of her enemies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 58.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>We haue againe among vs Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Martiniſtes, I vſe that name:<note place="margin">Socrat. eccl. hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as</hi> Libanius <hi>the Sophiſter in a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous libell againſt religion flattered</hi> Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>that hipocrite in profesſion, vntill hee
<pb facs="tcp:1109:17"/> came to the empyre, but afterwarde a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in perſecution:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>artiniſtes.</note> So <hi>Martin</hi> publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth manye his friuolous Pamphlets, bewraying in this, a ſpirite rather of ſcorne and ſlaunder, then learninge and loue, becauſe hee handleth diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie with ſcurrillitie, &amp; ſcripture with laughter, more pleaſant to a ſight of goſpell Libertines, and Churchrob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, then medling at all with the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hande, muche leſſe. deciding the controuerſies by moment and wayght of argument, and therefore better anſwered alreadie by ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie mates like himſelfe, then to bee vouchſafed ſo muche as a ſilable by learned replye: Theſe irregular fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes derrogate from Biſhops both title and place in Churche, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth. A verie ſore plague to the good eſtate and conſtitution of the Church, and a great deale the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, becauſe domeſticall and inwarde, and yet ſhall I ſaye my conſcience, and ſpeake indifferentlye? Fie for
<pb facs="tcp:1109:17"/> ſhame both <hi>Martin</hi> and <hi>Antemartin,</hi> Paciſcamur (ſayth <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi>) ſi placet vt nec tu malos nobis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ijcias, quos putas noſtros,<note place="margin">Aug. petilia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> nec ego veſtros vobis. <hi>Agreed (ſayth</hi> Auguſt. <hi>to</hi> Petilian) <hi>If you pleaſe, that neither you vpbrayde vs with thoſe on our part whom you thinke to be bad: Nor wee caſt you in teeth with ſuch on your ſide, as wee iudge verie ill of.</hi> So do yee both, and goe to the matter:<note place="margin">Ciprian. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Epiſt. <hi>9.</hi> Browniſtes.</note> But wee haue as miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous as anye the other: <hi>Puppianus Browniſtes,</hi> for they rightly follow his ſteppes, who as <hi>Ciprian</hi> writes would be <hi>perfect alone, vnſpotted, holy, pure, and not ioyne himſelfe with the reſt, but alone as it were in Paradiſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>in the kingdome of heauen, ſwelling with ſuch a pride, and puffed vp with ſuch arrogancie of minde, that he would reduce all biſhops, &amp; cleargie men to his owne knowledge to be purged before him, and to bee abſolued by his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: ſo that for the ſpace of</hi> 6. <hi>yeares, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had the fraternitie any Biſhop, nor the people an ouerſeer, nor the flocke a Paſtor,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:18"/> nor the Church a gouernour, nor Chriſt a Prelate, nor God anie Prieſt.</hi> Theſe ſet forth their bookes beyond all impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of all Schiſmatickes,<note place="margin">Magiſtrates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>egligence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ectes.</note> &amp; if they be let alone, as either impunitie, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of magiſtrates (I will not ſaye perciallytie) muſt needes further their faction, what maye the ſilie people thinke, whom they ſeduce daylie, and drawe into error, <hi>but that their doctrine is truer then ours</hi> &amp;, as they faſly obiect our Church of <hi>Englandes</hi> miniſterie, preaching,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ocrates lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> prayer, ſacraments, diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, is of no warrant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> ſomtime Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> in <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia,</hi> after his abdicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by a generall counſel, ſet a broch many wicked opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, among other, he did perſwade the people (deteſting other churches) to haue their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon meetings in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate houſes, drawing away ſeruaunts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their maiſters by ſimulation of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,<note place="margin">Brownistes Conuenticles.</note> the like are among vs, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all other aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies in accuſtomed churches, &amp; gathering themſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither
<pb facs="tcp:1109:18"/> in houſhold conuenticles, alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating prentices by coulor of religion from all duty of obedience, &amp; dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with their maiſters. I wiſh this ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of <hi>Ciprian</hi> were well learned of ſuch.<note place="margin">Ciprian ibid</note> Scire debes Epiſcopu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in eccleſia eſſe, et eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Epiſcopo, et ſi qui in Epiſcopo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſunt, in eccleſia non eſſe, et fruſtra ſibi blandiri eos qui pacem cum ſacerdotibus Dei non habentes, obrepunt et latenter apud quoſdam communicare ſe credunt cum eccleſia quae catholica et vna eſt, ſciſſa non ſit neque deuiſa, ſed vbique connecta et cohere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tium ſibi inuicem ſacerdotum glutino copulata. <hi>You ought to know that the Biſhop is in the church, and the church in the Biſhop, &amp; they are not in the church whoſoeuer they bee that are not in the Biſhop, and they doe vainelie flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues which hauing no peace with Gods Prieſtes commit themſelues in cloſe man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to bee pertakers with ſome certaine perſons whereas Gods Church being Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique is not rent nor deuided, but knit
<pb facs="tcp:1109:19"/> and coupled togither by faſt conſent of Miniſters of the Church agreeing one with another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Ioh. <hi>7.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> I will ſaye vnto them as ſomtime <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayd. Habemus ſpiritum ſanctum ſi amamus Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, amamus autem ſi in eius compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge et charitate conſtitimus. <hi>Wee haue the holie ſpirit if wee loue the Church, and wee loue it if wee perſiſt in vnitie and loue of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now all this while if there be anie that in ſingleneſſe of hart &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines of zeale deſires ſomthinges a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, I ſpeake not againſt them, for as I am not with them that vtterly blaſpheme and affirme wee haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aright,<note place="margin">As anone you ſhall heare to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward the end.</note> ſo I am not againſt them that diſcretly blame and accuſe ſome thinges amiſſe in the church: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is my meaning Good things looſe the grace of their goodneſſe, if they be not wel handled. Concertati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for reformation more eager and bitter a great deale, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is behoofefull or needfull, is like vnto madnes, <hi>a very
<pb facs="tcp:1109:19"/> ſeditiouſe vexation of the common wealth doth often follow the turbulent affection of the Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sozom. lib. <hi>8</hi> cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Emperour</hi> Conſtantine <hi>doth his parte, whoſe care is both to lead the people along in vniformitie of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. vita. Conſtan. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and heale the grieuous ſicknes of the bodie of the whole common wealth, and I hope the like be endeuoured by the Cleargie of the land that was ſignified by the Biſhops of the Eaſt to them of the west Church in their letters from their Synods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the neceſſarie great cace to recouer the Church: Nowe I would haue</hi> the people do as they of Antioch did, <hi>who for</hi> 30.<note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>yeares ſpace endured the</hi> Arrians <hi>ſchiſme with patience, ſtill hoping for a better day, vntill indeed their blaſphemie againſt the Apoſtles doctrine, and conſpiracie againſt chriſtians was intollerable.</hi> Then howe much more ought wee with longer patience among our ſelues tarrie for reformation of ſome things amis vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a better time,<note place="margin">Hope &amp; pray for reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſith wee haue more then 30. yeares now enioyed the free doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:20"/> and ſtill haue as much as euer wee can do to preuaile againſt the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; bloody enemies of the goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>art. Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie.</note>We come nowe to prophecie, the ſecond thing to be handled, the moſt excellent gift of all, the Apoſtle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not that peculiar prophecie, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling the comming of chriſt, &amp; fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threating the puniſhment of ſinne, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at</hi> Samuell,<note place="margin">Act. 3.24. Math. 11.3.</note> the number wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were frequent, before Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>but now very rare,</hi> but in the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce as he ſpeaketh elſe where. <hi>Let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie according to the proportion of faith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> And againe <hi>he that prophecieth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeaketh vnto men vnto aedifieng, and to exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to comfort,</hi> preferring it before all other giftes: For the ample vſe &amp; prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall benefit, for as all other giftes do reſpect <hi>the profite and aedification of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.11. 1. Cor. 12.7.</note> ſo prophecie eſpecially: <hi>For ſaluation cammeth by fayth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>fayth by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and hearing by the worde of God.</hi> It is the verye ſame wee call preaching, ſet downe in the ſcripture by the Apoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:1109:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> in variable phraſe of ſpeach, as theſe, <hi>apt to teach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.2. 2. Tim. 2.15 2. Tim. 4.2</note> 
               <hi>deuiding the worde of truth aright, preach the word, be inſtant in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and out of ſeaſon, improue, rebuke, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort with all long ſuffering and doctrines, holding faſt that faythfull word according, able to exhort by wholeſome doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.9. Tit. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>and conuince them that ſay contrarie: Speake the thinge whiche becommeth wholeſome doctrine.</hi> Therefore <hi>the whole ſcripture is called a moſt ſure worde of prophecie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19 20</note> 
               <hi>being of no priuate interpretation, becauſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie came not in old time by the will of man, but holye men of God ſpake, as they were moued by the holy ghoſt.</hi> As the vſe of all ſcriptures is very manifolde, <hi>for the whole ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and is profitable, to teach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.10</note> 
               <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, to correct, and to inſtruct in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, that the man of God may be abſolut, being made perfect vnto all good workes, and whatſoeuer thinges are written afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>time, are written for our learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>that wee throughe patience, and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Scriptures might haue hope:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:21"/> Right ſo hee that is furniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the qualities afore mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and can aplie the ſcriptures to the ſame end as ſhalbe requiſite, may be called in this ſence of the Apoſtle, a prophet of the goſpell. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith ſpeaking of Chriſt:<note place="margin">Aguſt. tho. <hi>6.</hi> tract. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> Erat autem do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus prophetarum, impletor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum, ſanctificator prophetarum, ſed et propheta, propheta dominus, et verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei dominus, et nullus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheta ſine verbo dei prophetat. Cum prophetis verbum dei, et prophetae verbum dei. Meruerunt priora tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora prophetas afflatos, et impletos verbo dei, mernimus nos prophetam. ipſum verbum dei. <hi>But it was he that ſet forth the prophets, fulfilled all thinges the prophets told ſhould happen, ſanctified the prophets, the Lord was that prophet, &amp; the Lord was that worde of God, and no prophet doth prophecie without gods word. In old time they had the benefit of prophets inſpired, and filled with the word of God, but we haue this pleaſure, the verie word of
<pb facs="tcp:1109:21"/> God to be our prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the gift which the Apoſtle acountes moſt excellente aboue the reſt, and therefore not common, but rare, not eaſie but difficulte, as be all thinges, which are excellent, for hee ſayth, <hi>he that ſpeaketh ſtraunge languages edifieth himſelfe, but he that prophecieth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Co. 14.4.12 13.</note> 
               <hi>edifieth the Church:</hi> Againe <hi>forasmuch as you couet ſpirituall giftes, ſeeke that you may excell, to the edifying of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">18.19.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; let him that ſpeaketh in a ſtraunge lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage pray that he may interpret.</hi> Againe <hi>he thanketh God, he ſpake languages more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the reſt, yet he</hi> had rather in the Church ſpeake fiue wordes with his vnderſtanding, that he might inſtruct others, then ten thouſand wordes in a ſtraunge tongue. This oughte to ſtrike into the hartes of all chriſtians a deeper conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a more god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dutie, and firſt of the miniſterie then of the multitude.</p>
            <p>Touching our ſelues to ſhu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſome faults verie common among vs:<note place="margin">Inſufficienci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of miniſters.</note> As
<pb facs="tcp:1109:22"/> firſt Inſufficiencie. For it is not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one to protrude, &amp; thruſt forth himſelfe vnto the calling with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane minde, only for the ſubſidie &amp; help of liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, &amp; not the benefit of the church, hauing nothing aboue the ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pacitie, and knowledge of the vulgar ſort, as though we were miraculouſlie to beleue <hi>that</hi> Saule <hi>is among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Sam. 19.24.</hi> Greg. nazian Apol. <hi>1.</hi> Item <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lend. Atha.</note> 
               <hi>Or that to become a mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene god &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue the very ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; meaning of chriſt, &amp; of his ſpirit, to be (as it were in the place of</hi> Angels <hi>and</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angels, <hi>to be euen a god, &amp; bring others to god, to handle that great body of Chriſt (the ſocietie of the church) were a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> both of facillity &amp; ſecurity,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.16.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed <hi>who is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for theſe things?</hi> Moyſes <hi>among the prieſts vneloquent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>of a ſlow mouth &amp; tongue, till god was in his mouth, and taught him what he ſhoulde ſay.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 66.</note> Eſay <hi>among the prophets a man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne, and of vncleane lips, vntil one of the</hi> Seraphins <hi>hauing an hote cole in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the altar, layd it vpon his mouth
<pb facs="tcp:1109:22"/> and touched his lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galat. 1.15. 1. Cor. 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo hee was ſent of the Lords meſſage. St.</hi> Paule <hi>among the Apoſtles, as one borne out of due time, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete to be called an apoſtle, but that God did ſeperate him from his mothers wombe, &amp; called him by grace to reueale his ſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ambroſ. in</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>and preach him among the gentils. Amb.</hi> ſaith, expounding the apoſtles words Prophetia eſt, qua eligitur quaſi doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor futurus idoneus, manus vero im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitiones verba ſunt miſtica quibus confirmatur ad hoc opus electus, acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens teſte conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia ſna vt audeat vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce domini ſacrificiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deo offerre. <hi>This is prophecie when one is choſen, as a meete man afterwards to teach the people, &amp; the hands laid on by the company of elderſhip, are words in a miſterie, by which the party thus choſen, is withall ſetled to this worke, and receaueth power, his owne conſcience bearing him witnes, that he may boldly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifice to god in the lords ſteed.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Vale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> after the death<note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Auxentius</hi> the <hi>Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had made this ſpeach to the ſynod of biſhops for the
<pb facs="tcp:1109:23"/> electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a biſhop, ſaying vnto them you cannot be ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being learned Diuines vnto what manner of men it is conuenient to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit the pontificall dignitie, euen ſuch a one as ought to inſtruct the people, not onlye with doctrine, but alſo with manners and life ſo propoſing himſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of perfect honeſty, that the godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his life may ſay for a witnes his doctrine is good, and therefore place him at this time in the Biſhopricke, to whom alſo euen our ſelues the rulers of the Empire may ſincerelie ſubmit our heades: And becauſe wee are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and muſt needes offend, may willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admit their reprehenſions as a cure by phiſicke. And thereuppon the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node willed the Emperour himſelfe by his voyce to make choyſe of one verie wiſe and godly man, hee replied thus: Maior, quam vt a me praeſtari poſſit, res eſt, multoque fuerit melius vos diſcernere diulna gratia dignatos et participes ſpendoris illius. <hi>It is a
<pb facs="tcp:1109:23"/> greater matter then I can performe, and it ſhalbe much better for your ſelfe to diſcerne whom gods grace hath vouchſaued worthy pertakers of his glorie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Chriſtian Emperour may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie well inſtruct vs, that the impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the handes of the Elderſhip in making a Miniſter ſhould follow firſt a dignitie of giftes by diſcretion of grace.<note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Apolog. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the dignitie of the Miniſterie, ſaith thus: <hi>VVhat a gods name is he that as if hee faſhion an Image out of clay in a ſhort dayes ſpace maketh a Miniſter (who is a defender of the truth) him (I ſay) that muſt be in the order and degree of Angels, celebrate the prayſe of God with Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, tranſmit the ſacrifices of the higheſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, execute the Prieſthood with Chriſt. I will ſay more, he that ſhall become as it were a God, and make others godes.</hi> This ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſhoulde be well obſerued both of Biſhops (ſuch I meane not all) as ſuddenly impoſe their hands on men vnmeet for the calling, <hi>&amp; ſo become per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers
<pb facs="tcp:1109:24"/> of their ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 5.20.</note> &amp; likewiſe of them that vnworthyly intrude themſelues into the functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing it as ordinary a matter to be made a miniſter, as for the potter to forme a ſhape out of clay or the regiſter to writ forth the orders, &amp; the Officials to clap to the Biſhops ſeale.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Negligence in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he miniſtrie.</note>An other fault is negligence. For many hauing verye notable giftes of god, &amp; withall the gift of prophecie, do cleane forget the Apoſtles rule, &amp; councell to <hi>Timothie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Deſpiſe not the gift that is in thee giuen by prophecie, and againe, that worthy thing that was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.6.14.</note> 
               <hi>keepe through the holye ghoſt, which dwelleth in vs. Likewiſe ſtir vp the gift of God which is in thee, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of my handes.</hi> Ambition of the worlde more then ſpirituall gifts, and loue of pleaſures, more then of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie carrie manie ſuch away. The Apoſtle can tell them that preaching in a Miniſter <hi>is a worke of neceſſitie layde vppon him, and his caſe is wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:24"/> if hee preache not the Goſpell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.16.17.</note> 
               <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther willinglye, or grudginlye, becauſe the diſpenſation is committed vnto him.</hi> I thinke there was neuer age afore vs ſoe excellent for manye floriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witts both in all kinde of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and in Deuinitie. The <hi>Spirite of Moyſes diſtributed verye commonlye and vniuerſallye vnto the</hi> Elders,<note place="margin">Num. 11.16.25.</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> Officers <hi>in the</hi> Tabernacle <hi>of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>and the Spirit of</hi> Elias <hi>dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vppon</hi> Elizeus. <hi>The worde of the Lorde is not rare, as in the dayes of</hi> Samuell,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 3.1. Eſay. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>but all the multitude of the people maye aſcende to the hill of the lord, to the houſe of god, and hee teacheth them his wayes that they maye walke in his pathes.</hi> Manye for all that neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their giftes, and become volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wantons of the world, ſeldom or neuer exerciſed in Preaching to the people. That order in the church ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of before, brings with it a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie care of dutie.<note place="margin">Aug. ſerm. temp. <hi>165.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith Habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus duo quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plane diſtinguenda,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:25"/> vnum quod chriſtiani ſumus, alterum quod prepoſiti ſumus: Chriſtiani propter nos, prepoſiti propter vos: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto quod chriſtiani ſumus vnde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem reddimus deo de vita noſtra, ſumus etiam prepoſiti vnde rationem reddimus deo de diſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſatione noſtra. Wee <hi>(of the Cleargie)</hi> haue two things plainelie to be diſtinguiſhed <hi>(from you of the Laitie) The one is that wee are Chriſtians, the other, that wee are placed ouer you: We are Chriſtians for our owne ſelues, but ſet ouer you for your ſakes. Beſids this that wee are Chriſtians, and thereby render accompt to God for our owne life, we are rulers ouer you, and by that meanes giue accompt of the diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited vnto vs.</hi> I ſpare the reuerende Biſhops of the land, and other auncient fathers, ſuch as haue laboured in doctrine diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, when they were younge, but are vnable to ſuſtaine, and vnapt to execute the like for defect of nature, and feeblenes of age, I wiſh them yet to do as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> writes to
<pb facs="tcp:1109:25"/> to his father.<note place="margin">Greg. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an. Apolog. poſt. ex fuga red. iter. paſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> orat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Duplicem pro ſimplici dat ſeipſum ſenectutis que ſubſidium, ſpiritus ſubſidium facit. <hi>Hee giueth you too for one, and maketh a ſupplie of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, an ayd of his age.</hi> For being conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med himſelfe with yeares, he did aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate his ſonne, whoe was a double ſteede and aide vnto him (to wit) of his auncient yeares and giftes of the ſpirit, vpholding his father bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with weakenes, and bearing with him the ſpirituall cares of the church. So ſhoulde aged Prelates do, procure and alure young men of worthie gifts to be coadiutors in their infirmities, and accordinglye rewarde them the better to maintaine them in ſtudie, &amp; the more to incourage them in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. Nowe if there be anye ſuch as <hi>Gregorie</hi> writes of beſides, cui vel altiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima ſenectus canam doctrinam attu, lerit, eam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vim habentem vt nouae in pietate animae vtilitate at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento eſſe queat. <hi>Whom extreame olde age hath brought vnto an auncient kynde
<pb facs="tcp:1109:26"/> of preaching, and the ſame ſo effectuall, that he can with a godlie mind doe good, and helpe to labour (in the Church) as much as hee did before.</hi> That as <hi>Moyſes was foureſcore yeares olde when hee ſpake to</hi> Pharao,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſo any one or other of lyke years decreeth with</hi> himſelfe that hee will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin againe his former trauell in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the goſpell, I eſteeme ſuch a one not only reuerend among men, but alſo greatlie bleſſed of God. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomen</hi> writes of one <hi>Theonas</hi> verye learned in the doctrine of <hi>Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sozom. lib. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Grecians</hi> and <hi>Latins,</hi> who for thirtie yeares ſpace liued in ſilence. If there bee anye ſuche amonge vs of the Miniſterie ſufficientlye ſeene in varietie, and diuerſitie of learning, that haue vſed ſilence nowe this foure and thirtie yeares ſpace in ſo religious and bleſſed a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>agation of the Goſpell, howe they will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare for manie a ſoule periſhing in ignoraunce long of their neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I leaue it to god, &amp; their owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1109:26"/>
            <p>Wee maye adde a thirde faulte to both the former, which is ſimonie:<note place="margin">Symonie in miniſters.</note> For wee couet not ſpirituall giftes, but ſpirituall promotions, not the calling, but the liuing, not the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, but the benefices of the church. I ſay as <hi>Barnard</hi> ſomtime to <hi>Eugeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. conſi. Eug. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Vides omnem eccleſiaſticum ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum feruere ſola pro dignitate tuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, honori totum datur, ſanctitati ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil aut parum? <hi>Perceiue you the zeale of our Church; men how earneſt they are only to maintayne their dignetie? All is for eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nothing a doe for holynes, or very litle.</hi> I would handle this matter more largly, if I thought I did ſpeake to ſuch a people who, as ye do iuſtlie finde faulte with the miniſtrie, ſo yee would diſcreetly take heed ye apply it not to the froward offence of youre owne fayth, and ſhamfull reproch of our caling: but rather be firſt religious to amende your ſelues, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to reprehende vs. Conſidering what Augſtuſtin ſayth, Par cauſa et
<pb facs="tcp:1109:27"/> docentem et audientem conſtringit vt vtriuſque cofeſſio factorum teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatione ſignetur,<note place="margin">Aug. math. ſerm. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> iungantur factis, qui ſeperantur officijs, copulentur o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, qui diuerſi ſunt nomine, et quos vocabula ab inuicem ſeperant, eos obſeruantia praeceptorum fideliter et deuote coniungat. <hi>The like reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines both the preacher and the hearer, that their workes bearing witneſſe may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token both their confeſſions: let them bee ioyned in deedes, that are ſet apart in offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: coupled in workes that are diuers in names, and let the reuerence of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements ioyne them faythfully, and deuoutly togither whom titles ſeperate one from an other.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Orat. ad Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor. Niſsen.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> writing to <hi>Gregorie Niſſen:</hi> I woulde ſayth he very gladly ſpeake ſomwhat boulder, but I am moued with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of the day to ſaye nothinge ſharplie or vnluckely. Perhaps hee woulde not diſpleaſe the eares, or greiue the conſciences, or offend the fayth of ſeelye chriſtians, by telling
<pb facs="tcp:1109:27"/> them of the vncleane ſacrifices of the heathcn: euen ſo I deſire to ſpeake more boldlye of ſome thinges, but moued with the reuerence of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I will ſay nothing vngentlye, or vnluckely, partlie becauſe of <hi>Libertins</hi> that will by and by ſnatch occaſion to blaſpheme the holynes of the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and partlie for hypocrits that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſpie the motes of ſimonie in vs, but not ſee the beames of ſacriledge in themſelues.<note place="margin">Math. 27.4.</note> I will not ſay (no in deed will I not) <hi>that with</hi> Iudas, <hi>wee ſell Chriſt, betraying the ſecond time the blood of the innocent.</hi> Neither can I ſay with Symon,<note place="margin">Act. 8 19.</note> wee <hi>buy the giftes of the holye ghoſt.</hi> Symon <hi>in deed of experience would haue bought them, but hee could not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſil. epiſt.</hi> 76. Math. 10.8.</note> yet this I will ſaie that with Iudas <hi>we loue the bagge &amp; hauing it freely giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>we do not beſtowe it as freely:</hi> and that <hi>with the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes <hi>wee worſhip</hi> Mercurie <hi>too muche that god with a purſe in his right hande.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euag. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> One <hi>Iohn Presbiter</hi> after the death of <hi>Timothie</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> by
<pb facs="tcp:1109:28"/> iurie &amp; ſimonie gat the biſhoricke, but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Zeno</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> vnderſtood it, he put him out &amp; placed <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſtead writing an epiſtle <hi>(te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord) called (henoticon)</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould ſubſcribe to the ſame epiſtle.<note place="margin">Euag. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> But <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtaſius</hi> biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> when <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the <hi>Emperor</hi> (after he was biſhop) aſked him a ſumme of monie &amp; thruſt him out becauſe he denied (as the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> reporteth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other) like a very godly biſhop, did willingly ſuffer depriuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Iohn Chriſoſtome</hi> the <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in his viſitation in <hi>Aſia</hi> vnderſtanding that manye by gifts,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ozom. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> &amp; fauour did buy &amp; ſell benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, came to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and for <hi>ſimonie</hi> de priued 13. biſhops at once, ſome of <hi>Li ſia,</hi> ſome of <hi>Phrigia,</hi> ſome of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Now if there be any among vs (I ſay if there bee anye, for I proteſt perticularlie I meane not any, much les maliciouſly accuſe any) who rather like <hi>Iohn Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biter</hi> will get a biſhopricke, or eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall promotion by periurie and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:28"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> ſuffer eiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rather then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mmit ſimonie. I do wiſh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t our <hi>Zeno</hi> woulde remoue <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp; ſurrogate <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Elizabeth.</note> but with this condition,<note place="margin">Io. Archbiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cant. and Yorke. Anglia.</note> that he obſerue the epiſtle of concord, and that <hi>Iohn Patriarch</hi> would make his viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Aſia</hi> &amp; ſpy out as in my cleargy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as come in by ſimonie, ſome in one dioces, &amp; ſome in an other, and put them out, if there be 13. biſhops at a clap.<note place="margin">Ambroſ. epiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. <hi>50.</hi> orat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Auxent.</note> Shall <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be heard. Quid ſunt cathedrae niſi honores, quid ſunt columbae niſi mentes ſimplices, vel animae fidem ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didam &amp; puram ſequentes, ergo iube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exire qui dignitates vendit et ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores, iubetur exire qui vendere vult ſimplices mentes fideliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>What are the ſeates but places of honour, what are the doues, but the ſeelie mindes &amp; ſoules of ſuch as followe the cleare and pure fayth, then he is commaunded to go forth of the church that ſells dignities and honours, he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to go out of the church that will ſell the ſeelie conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the faithful.
<pb facs="tcp:1109:29"/> Baſill</hi> doth call it tranſitum ad Gehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan, <hi>Hellferrie,</hi> and ſo I feare me it is in deed both for the prieſt &amp; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>Barnard</hi> tels a tale of <hi>Martin</hi> a Cardinaall prelate whoe returning in his Legacie from <hi>Dacia</hi> was ſo poore (his money and horſes fayling him) that he coulde ſcarſe come to <hi>Florence.</hi> The Biſhop of <hi>Florence</hi> gaue him a horſe which brought him to <hi>Piſe,</hi> where <hi>Barnard</hi> reporteth he was at the ſame time: the next daye after the Biſhop of <hi>Florence</hi> came to <hi>Piſe,</hi> &amp; requiring for the diſpatch of ſome cauſe hee had in lawe the teſtimonie of his freindes, preſuming of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall amonge the reſt, for his late good turne, came to him for his voice, then ſayde <hi>Martin</hi> you haue deceiued mee ſir, I litle knewe ye had ſuch buſines in hand, &amp; the very ſame houre reſigned his horſe. <hi>Barnard</hi> bringes this in to vpbrayde both the inſolencie and ſimonie of the Court of Rome in Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:1109:29"/> 
               <hi>Martin</hi> paſſing throughe a Countrie of gold and ſiluer tooke no knowledge of it, &amp; moreouer would not be ſo much as ſuſpected to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gift at all. As litle as I like <hi>Martin Marprelate,</hi> ſurelie this was <hi>Martin good-prelate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martin good prelat.</note> and I would to God that euery one both Biſhop and other mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter were ſuch a <hi>Martin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now concerning your ſelues of the Auditory.<note place="margin">Contempt in the common people.</note> Manie faultes likewiſe are common in you: Contempt of <hi>Prophecie</hi> is one and the firſt. For whereas the end of this notable gift of <hi>Prophecie</hi> is edification (as ye heard afore) the people in theſe daies are growne to a hatefull contempt, and rebellious diſobeidience of the word preached, as the Prophet ſayd in his time.<note place="margin">Ierm. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>The warning of the Prophets is but winde, the worde of God is not in them. They ſay prophecie not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 2.6.11.</note> 
               <hi>yee ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie vnto vs, no ye ſhall not.</hi> Euerye paynfull miniſter may finde <hi>Bernards</hi> wordes to be true.<note place="margin">Berna. cant. ſerm. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> Coarctore duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,
<pb facs="tcp:1109:30"/> et quid eligam neſcio: placere ne mihi in eo quod locutus ſum, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam quod debui feci, an penitentiam agere ſuper verbo meo, quia quod vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lui, non recepi. Beſids a threefold pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of the labour and worke in reſpect of our ſelues, conſcience, intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, vtteraunce, Conſcience to be rightlie called by inward teſtimonie. Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to perceiue the deuine ſence of the ſcripture, vtteraunce to teach the people, (of which three, the firſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit, the ſecond hard, the thirde in maner harder then the ſecond) yee do ad a threefold harder difficultie then all, &amp; that is to procure your teacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes in hearing, faythfulnes in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing, holineſſe in obeying. For <hi>oh! Lord who hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> credence to our preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 53.1. Rom. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. Eſay. 65.2. Rom. 10.21.</note> 
               <hi>or who hath beleeued our report. All the day long do we ſtretch forth our hands to a diſobedient &amp; gaynſaying people, but erre not I pray you and bee not deceiued.</hi> Greater far authority, is the propheſie in the goſpell, then of old: &amp; far more
<pb facs="tcp:1109:30"/> fearefull to diſpiſe the one, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the other. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11.6</note> 
               <hi>more then a prophet, none greater among me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of women, &amp; yet the leaſt in the kingdome of heauen greater then hee.</hi> The Apoſtle commaundes vs not <hi>to deſpiſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying, for no doubt hee that deſpiſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.19 1. Theſ. 4.8. 1. Sam. 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth not man but god, who hath giuen you his holy ſpirit:</hi> The Lord ſayd to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell</hi> the prophet. <hi>They haue not caſt thee away, but caſt me away,</hi> &amp; ſo ſayde Chriſt to his diſciples,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>He that heareth you, heareth mee, and he that diſpiſeth you, diſpiſeth me, &amp; he that diſpiſeth me, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him that ſent me.</hi> And in deed all former prophets in their viſions did leuell with their eyes, and looke ſtrait on Chriſt the only prophet of all. <hi>To him al gaue witnes that through his name al that beleue in him ſhould receaue remis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes.</hi> Ambroſe ſaith:<note place="margin">Act. 10.43. <hi>Amb. Luc.</hi> 9. <hi>lib.</hi> 7.</note> Et hodie <hi>Moſes</hi> docet, et hodie <hi>Elias</hi> loquitur, et hodie in maiori gloria <hi>Moſen</hi> videre poſſimus. <hi>Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now a dayes Moſes teacheth and now a dayes</hi> Elias <hi>ſpeaketh, and now a
<pb facs="tcp:1109:31"/> dayes wee may ſee Moyſes in a great deale more glorie.</hi> Nay <hi>Barnard</hi> ſeemeth to require the grace of prophecie in as manie of your ſelues as are deuout and godlie. For ſaith hee, Vbi angelica in hoc corpore conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, in corde prophetica expectatio in vtroque apoſtolica perfectio inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, gratus iſte cumulus gratiarum. <hi>Where we haue in this (our) bodie a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like vnto the Angels in the hart: an hope as the prophets had in both: the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how great an aboundance is it of Gods graces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Arogancie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he people.</note>Arrogancie is an other fault in our people: For manie haue a dedignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bee taught, ſurmiſing themſelues more ſufficiently to haue the ſence of the spirit, and ſincerlie the knowledg of the truth, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any learned preacher of them all. As though it were a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trit &amp; baſe matter that St. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>to ſearch the deepe things of God.</hi> And whereas the Apoſtle would <hi>haue the ſpirits euen of the</hi> Prophets <hi>ſubiecte</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 14.32.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:31"/> 
               <hi>to the</hi> Prophets,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.20 2. Tim. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Cor. 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> theſe will admit no cenſure of anie elſe, but onlie their owne <hi>priuate interpretation,</hi> yet being no Prophets, as though <hi>Prophecie were of priuate interpretation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. nazia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Theol. orat. <hi>1</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>all were Apoſtles, all Prophets, all Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> writeth of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomius,</hi> who as though <hi>hee were rapt into heauen after</hi> Elias,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 2.11</note> 
               <hi>made worthye to talke with God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.9.</note> 
               <hi>and beholde him in a cloud after</hi> Moyſes, <hi>taken vp into</hi> Paradice, &amp; <hi>hearing imposſible things to be vttered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Paule,</hi> doth (ſayth he) in one daies ſpace make manie mo Sainctes, and creat deuines (as it were) inſpiring learning into them, &amp; cauſing many conuenticles of vnlearned praters, and of ſuch an immediate vpſtart ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit aboue the ſober and modeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of lawfull knowledge, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the reſt of the miniſterie, &amp; people of God, altogither in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, in cloudes,<note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moder. diſpu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> habend.</note> in the paradiſe with God himſelfe are thoſe I ſpeake of. A dayes <hi>diſpatch for deuinitie is enough
<pb facs="tcp:1109:32"/> with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. They come out of the ſchoole of</hi> Conciſion. <hi>Hee or ſhe that hath raſhlie learned two or three wordes of ſcripture,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſtraight wayes fals a building of</hi> Babell <hi>that their name maie be ſcattered abroade vpon the whole earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 16.2.</note> And by and by <hi>muſt</hi> Corah <hi>and his companie furiouſly ſtirre vp an inſurrection againſt Moyſes</hi> making in deed (which is miſerable) a ſcattered confuſion abroad of the Church, and a like holynes of office in the miniſters, and euerie one of the congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. I would to god withall my hart,<note place="margin">Num. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>that all the lords people could pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phecie, &amp; that the lord would put his ſpirit vpon them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; I will all chriſtians to ſearch the ſcriptures, for in them is eternity of life, and teſtimonie of chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 17.11.</note> 
               <hi>euen to be exquiſit examiners of doctrine, as were thoſe nobler men then thoſe of Theſſolonica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>and not to beleeue euery ſpirit, but try the ſpirites whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are of god ſo many falſe prophets are abroad in the world.</hi> I am not of the iudgement that olde <hi>Apelles</hi> was who thought <hi>that euery man ought to holde</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſ lib. <hi>5.</hi> eccl <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:32"/> 
               <hi>opinion as he beleeued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Eccl. hiſtor. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and is not at all to examine any doctrine.</hi> But rather of an o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther minde <hi>teaching the vtilitie and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesſitie of ſcripture, that the ſcriptures in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by god, do caſt ſeedes of wonderfull precepts of doctrine teaching matters in deede very deuine, notable godlines, and a right rule of life, into the hartes of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorie, and do propoſe a verie holy religion to ſuch as ſtudie them. But they do not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the art of Logique, whereby to reſiſt them that oppugne the truth. Foraſmuch as we do then moſt eaſilie conquere the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, when we vſe our owne weapons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</hi> And therefore I do wiſh that euerie chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were like to <hi>Samoſata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>4</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Eccl. hiſtor. ap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> who when their biſhop gaue vp the ſea, and <hi>Lucius</hi> a wolfe and traytor came in his roome, being ſpoyled of their Paſtor, tamen officia paſtoris exe quebantur, nam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctrina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruaba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam. <hi>For all that did execute their paſtors offices the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; kept the incorrupt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the apoſtles.</hi> But my deſire is that
<pb facs="tcp:1109:33"/> great deale more ſobrietie be <hi>in mans profeſſors, and that an order be kept in the execution of giftes, that ſome teach, and ſome learne, ſome to bee like the tongue, and ſome the eare, and the flocke ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the paſtors office, nor the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier guide the Armie which belonges to the Captaine. As it is expedient for a prouident Marchaunt, whoſe calling is to trauell the ieoperdouſe ſeas for commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſomtimes to bee in tranquillitie and quiet on the land: So in controuerſie and ſcruple of matter in</hi> religion, ſomtimes diſcipline with ſoberneſſe more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemeth a godlie people then diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations with frowardnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. cant. ſer.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. <hi>in</hi> 1. Cor. 8.2.</note> 
               <hi>Barnard</hi> ſayth vppon theſe wordes of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Now if anie man think that he knoweth any thing, hee knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as hee ought to knowe: Vides quoniam non probat multa ſcientem, ſi ſcientiae modum neſcierit, <hi>for you ſee that hee likes not a man, that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth much, &amp; is ignorant of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vnderſtanding,</hi> noting after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes
<pb facs="tcp:1109:33"/> the maner of knowledge to conſiſt in theſe poynts: Ordine, Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio, Fine. Ordine id prius quod matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ad ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Studio id arde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius quod vemehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius ad amore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fine vt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gloria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aut curioſitatem, aut aliquid ſimile, ſed tantum ad aedificationem tuam et proximi. <hi>In the order, endeuour, purpoſe. Touching the order (to knowe) that formoſt, which is ſpeedieſt to ſaluatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. concerning his indeuour that more ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſlie, which is more vehement to loue. As for the end that if it be not for vaine glorie, or curioſitie, or any like matter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">This part fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing was cut of: for time was p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; ouerſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it the other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> partes afore. Sacriledge in the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tie.</note> 
               <hi>but only to aedifie thy ſelfe, and thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An other fault and exceeding both the other is your ſacriledge, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie couetouſnes &amp; both honourable and worſhipfull Idoll of Proteſtants: but alas the ſpoyle of the church, and hinderaunce of prophecie. For what an impietie is this? Wee muſt haue the giftes of holye ſpirit,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.7.</note> and ye the <hi>giftes of holie Church, wee prophecie and preach the goſpell, and yee lyue of the
<pb facs="tcp:1109:34"/> goſpel: like mercenary ſouldiers ye ſend vs to warre, and be at no charges your ſelues. Nay you put our money, &amp; paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in your own purſes, ye will haue vs plant the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, &amp; not taſt of the fruit, but your ſelues wilbe dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke with the grapes therof.</hi> You ſay it is <hi>our calling to feede the flocke, and will not let vs eate of the milke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 21.24.</note> 
               <hi>But your owne breſtes are full of milke, &amp; your bones ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n full of marrow: you will haue vs neuer out of the tempel, &amp; yet you will take away</hi> the offerings, &amp; the gold of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. It is true that I tell you, your ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge is the very cauſe of our ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: for if we had a law ſure enough to cut of your ſacriledge, we could find a libertie ſoone enough to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit no ſimonie, &amp; without doubt we are not ſo deepe in the iudgments of god for ſimony, but ye are the former and the farther in for ſacriledge. And as wee ſhall anſwere for our owne ſelues, ſo ſhall ye anſwere both for your ſelues and vs alſo. I find not ſo great a cauſe of ſuch a number of poore in this la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
<pb facs="tcp:1109:34"/> as this your ſacriledge. Your robberie of the church is the robberie of the poore. <hi>Amb.</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amb. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 31. Eſay. 3.14.</note> Poſſeſſio eccleſiae ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptus eſt egenoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>The church liuings, are the maintenanece of the poore. The Lord muſt needs haue a controuerſie, and iudgement, with the auncient of the people, they waſt his vineyard, the ſpoyle of the poore is in their houſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 14.26.</note> Call ye me this a proteſtaunt, when a <hi>man hath money, oxen, ſheepe, or ſtrong drinke, or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his hart deſireth, &amp; eateth it before the lord his god, and reioyceth both he and his familie, but neuer bringeth foorth anye tithes of his increaſe for the</hi> Leuit <hi>within his gate, that hath no inheritaunce with him, &amp; forgetteth the ſtraunger &amp; father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, &amp; widow, which ſhould likewiſe eat &amp; bee filled, that God might bleſſe him the more in all the workes of his hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 2.22. Epheſ. 5.5.</note> as the Apoſtle ſaith to the Iew. <hi>Thou that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreſt Idols, committeſt thou ſacriledge? So I to</hi> ſuch a proteſtaunt: <hi>Thou that ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horreſt poperie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. Ioh. tract. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>commiteſt thou idolatrie I meane ſacriledge? Auguſt.</hi> ſaith of <hi>Iudas</hi> that he was, fur ſacrilegus, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qualiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
               <pb facs="tcp:1109:35"/> fur, fur loculorum, ſed domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loculoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſed ſacroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fur ſacre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligus qui auſus fuerit vndecun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere, hoc eſt de eccleſia tollere. Qui a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid de eccleſia furatur, Iudae perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to comparatur. <hi>A ſacrilegious theife, not a common theife, that ſtole out of the lords coffers.</hi> A <hi>ſacrilegious theife that durſt ſteale wherſoeuer it was to be had, euen out of the church. Who ſo ſtealeth ought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church, is like</hi> Iudas <hi>that child of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul. arat. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> nameth ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be impietatem auaritia cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Euſeb. vita Conſtant. lib. cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>A hughe heape of vngodlie coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes.</hi> In the daies of Conſtantine, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any martyrs or confeſſors died, or baniſhed perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hauing no kinred ſuruiuing to poſſes their inheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it came to the church of that place, &amp; if any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before named, had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of their poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to the church, it was to remaine ſure for euer to the church. There be many that can find fault with our couetouſnes, but not <hi>with that couetouſnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, a huge heape of all impietie.</hi> They can ſpie out
<pb facs="tcp:1109:35"/> 
               <hi>Magus for ſimonie among vs, but not</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das <hi>for ſacriledge amongſt themſelues: they thinke the Church goodes which they poſſes to be their rightfull patrimonie and inheritaunce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal 83.12 <hi>Bern. Epiſtol.</hi> 42.</note> 
               <hi>which I ſee not how it maye be vnles they will ſay, let vs take the ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie of god for our poſſesſions,</hi> for in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie deed the church goods are poore mens poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not an inheritaunce for noble men and gentelmen. But I feare me it will at lenth be the decaie of both our floriſhing Vniuerſities, where verie manye of rare giftes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther betake themſelues to an other calling abroad, or abide cloſe at their ſtudie in the vniuerſitie, their giftes being hid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world, becauſe they ſee the reward of their labour taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſo that they cannot procure a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſo vnſatiable in a number of you is your couetous ſacriledge. You will ſay vnto me, we do not ſee, but your ſelues of the cleargie are as faultie as we of the laity, for we could not ſell if ye did not buie, naie manie will offer
<pb facs="tcp:1109:36"/> and that verie roundlie &amp; larglie out of their liuing, to haue the dignitie <hi>&amp;</hi> title, I cannot tell whether anie do ſo. And I tiowe you ſpeake not againſte lawfull titles, but ambition of them: For otherwiſe I ſee not but they are lawfull in reuerend biſhops, ſo it bee as <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith cant. ſerm. 33. Pro hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſmodi volunt eſſe, &amp; ſunt eccleſiaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Praepoſiti, Deca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i, Archidiaconi, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi, Archiepiſcopi. <hi>For theſe like things (ſpeaking before of the voluptuouſe pride in the Cleargie) both they are, and co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uet to bee eccleſiaſticall Prelates, Deanes, Archdeacons, Biſhops, Archbiſhops. Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzen</hi> ſaith againſt the indignitie,<note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Maxius.</note> and ambition of ſuch as <hi>Maximus,</hi> who of a Cinicke philoſopher ſo quicklie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a chriſtian, and ſought by ſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to tranſlate the chaire to himſelfe. Vtinam nulla eſſet throni praerogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, nec praelatio et violenta authoritas ac praeemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, vt ex ſola virtute cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſceremur. <hi>I would god there were noe prerogatiue of throne, nor praeferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent authoritie &amp; praeheminence, that wee
<pb facs="tcp:1109:36"/> might bee knowne by vertue alone.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the ſame auncient father appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth a ſuperioritie and preferment of biſhops, ſo it come by degrees, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, as he ſpeakes of <hi>Baſill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Nazia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in laudem Baſilij.</note> 
               <hi>who was firſt a reader of deuinitie, then an elder, &amp; afterwards placed in the biſhops chaire de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruedlie.</hi> And againe ſaith that <hi>Baſill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>had a principall care and indeuor</hi> antiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem obſeruare <hi>(meaning Euſebius) and did poſſeſſe the gouernment of the Church, though hee were ſeconde in honor of the</hi> Chayre to Euſebius. I told you before I take no perticuler knowledg of ani ſuch, but if there bee anie ſuch I am ſuer Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe durſt not for his life deliuer the goods of the church. For ſayth hee, they were giuen me to kepe them, but not to paſſe them away. The ſame father ſayth of Auxentius the Arria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Ambro. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Epiſt. orat. in Auxent.</note> who tooke vpon him an other name to bee called Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius. Vnum portentum eſt duo nomina, mutauit vocabulum, ſed perfideam non mutauit, exuit Lupum, et induit Lupum. <hi>One monſter, but two names, he chaunged his title, but not his treacherie, he put a woolfe off, and one verie cunninglie.</hi> And ſo I ſay of euery ſuch a one. Call him Mercurius, but hee is ſtill Auxentius the
<pb facs="tcp:1109:37"/> Atria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. One monſter though he haue diuers names he hath chaunged his title, but not left his naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, he can put a wolfes ſkine of &amp; on verie well. Whither in the ende the feircenes of ſacriledge in you, &amp; ſimonie in vs will run, god alone knoweth, &amp; we may feare. The inrode is made already into the church, the incurſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will follow next vppon Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnons, afterwards the inuaſion wilbe to the ſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſeate of the Higheſt. And then will theſe ouerrune the land, confuſion for eſtate of order in the common wealth, barbarouſnes for ciuilitie of conuerſation amongſt the people, rebellion for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of lawes in ſubiects, ignoraunce for artes of learning in the vniuerſities. Atheiſme for religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God among chriſtians. But o Lorde in mercie turne away ſo feareful puniſhments from the land. My concluſion is As god beſtoweth diuers gifts of the ſpirit to the edefieng of his Church, ſo wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him by grace of the ſame ſpirite to make vs more painefull, your ſelues more thankfull, and all of vs more fruitfull, that following the truth in loue euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber doing his part to builde vp the bodie, wee may grow vp togither in him the heade of the ſame bodie Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour: To whom with the father and the holy ſpirit, be all prayſe honor and glorie euermore Amen.</p>
            <p>Manie things are amiſſe in the print, for ortographie, poynting, quoting, of places, ſence, and true Laten: Good Reader peruſe it with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight iudgement.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
